<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title>Geekaholic adventures</title>
  <link href="http://geekaholic.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://geekaholic.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2011-09-03T12:46:11+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://geekaholic.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Bud</name>
    
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title>Getting Down With Markdown</title>
    <link href="http://geekaholic.github.com/blog/2011/09/02/getting-down-with-markdown/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-02T10:46:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://geekaholic.github.com/blog/2011/09/02/getting-down-with-markdown</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I've been looking for an alternative to  &lt;a href=&quot;docbook.org&quot;&gt;docbook&lt;/a&gt;, which I've used for most of my tutorial handouts and internal developer documentation at &lt;a href=&quot;thinkcube.com&quot;&gt;Thinkcube&lt;/a&gt;. But the more I used it docbook the more I wanted a simpler solution which didn't require me to make sure my XML was in order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, at first I thought I'd try &lt;a href=&quot;latex-project.org&quot;&gt;Latex&lt;/a&gt; since it had a pretty good wrap with geeks and has even &lt;a href=&quot;http://openwetware.org/wiki/Word_vs._LaTeX&quot;&gt;surpassed usability expectations&lt;/a&gt; set forth by some of the mainstream wordprecessors :). What I loved about Latex was you could concentrate on the content first and formatting later. Its legendary ability to output desktop publishing quality documents and  convert to a variety of formats such as html, pdf or odt was a killer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as I was about to dive into Latex, &lt;a href=&quot;twitter.com/chanux&quot;&gt;Chanux&lt;/a&gt; suggested &lt;a href=&quot;daringfireball.net/projects/markdown&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; as an alternative. Hmm, Markdown, I pondered... I even liked the sound of it. It turns out Markdown is even better! You could think of it as a simplified wiki syntax but a better description would be to call it a WYSIWYG wiki syntax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; I've always endorsed the &lt;a href=&quot;en.wikipedia.org/wiki/KISS_principle&quot;&gt;KISS&lt;/a&gt; philosophy. There is nothing more simple and satisfying than to write a text file using &lt;a href=&quot;vim.org&quot;&gt;vim&lt;/a&gt; and track its progress via &lt;a href=&quot;git-scm.com&quot;&gt;git&lt;/a&gt;. After briefly going through the syntax, I realized this is exactly what I needed. I also realized that I had already used Markdown without actually thinking about it as part of using &lt;a href=&quot;github.com&quot;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; for a pet project. Everything about Markdown was all good and the whole &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zdnet.com/blog/violetblue/when-software-offends-the-pantyshot-package-controversy/509&quot;&gt;controversy&lt;/a&gt; around Markdown's html compiler names were exactly the kind of celebrity gossip it needed to grab attention!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was around this time, I was due to create a note for a tutorial for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.icter.org/UCSCConf/index.php/icter/ICTer2011/schedConf/workshops&quot;&gt;ICTer workshop&lt;/a&gt; myself and Dr. Ajantha from UCSC was to deliver. By now, I had decided on Markdown with &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/chobie/upskirt&quot;&gt;upskirt&lt;/a&gt; (yes this is one of the controversal names) to create the notes but what about the slides? Could I use Markdown for that as well? After a little looking around, I found a wonderful system called &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adamzap/landslide&quot;&gt;Landslide&lt;/a&gt; which enabled me to compile Markdown syntax into a beautiful html5 slide show presentation. After a little playing around I managed to build slides as well as the note using a single markdown source code! How cool was that? I will write a separate post soon on the HOWTO details but for now enjoy the &lt;a href=&quot;http://geekaholic.github.com/slides&quot;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;, if thats your cup of tea. My Markdown adventures don't end there. This post too was written using Markdown and converted to html using &lt;a href=&quot;octopress.org&quot;&gt;octopress&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
